<schema type="ZEO">

  <!-- XXX This schema still needs logging support. -->

  <description>
    This schema describes the configuration of the ZEO storage server
    process.
  </description>

  <!-- Use the storage types defined by ZODB. -->
  <import src="../ZODB/config.xml"/>

  <key name="address" datatype="socket-address"
       required="yes">
    <description>
      The address at which the server should listen.  This can be in
      the form 'host:port' to signify a TCP/IP connection or a
      pathname string to signify a Unix domain socket connection (at
      least one '/' is required).  A hostname may be a DNS name or a
      dotted IP address.  If the hostname is omitted, the platform's
      default behavior is used when binding the listening socket (''
      is passed to socket.bind() as the hostname portion of the
      address).
    </description>
  </key>

  <key name="read-only" datatype="boolean"
       required="no"
       default="false">
    <description>
      Flag indicating whether the server should operate in read-only
      mode.  Defaults to false.  Note that even if the server is
      operating in writable mode, individual storages may still be
      read-only.  But if the server is in read-only mode, no write
      operations are allowed, even if the storages are writable.  Note
      that pack() is considered a read-only operation.
    </description>
  </key>

  <key name="invalidation-queue-size" datatype="integer"
       required="no"
       default="100">
    <description>
      The storage server keeps a queue of the objects modified by the
      last N transactions, where N == invalidation_queue_size.  This
      queue is used to speed client cache verification when a client
      disconnects for a short period of time.
    </description>
  </key>

  <key name="transaction-timeout" datatype="integer"
       required="no">
    <description>
      The maximum amount of time to wait for a transaction to commit
      after acquiring the storage lock, specified in seconds.  If the
      transaction takes too long, the client connection will be closed
      and the transaction aborted.
    </description>
  </key>

  <key name="monitor-address" datatype="socket-address" required="no">
    <description>
      The address at which the monitor server should listen.  If
      specified, a monitor server is started.  The monitor server
      provides server statistics in a simple text format.
    </description>
  </key>

  <multisection name="+" type="storage"
                attribute="storages"
                required="yes">
    <description>
      One or more storages that are provided by the ZEO server.  The
      section names are used as the storage names, and must be unique
      within each ZEO storage server.  Traditionally, these names
      represent small integers starting at '1'.
    </description>
  </multisection>
</schema>
